Guide to John Well-Off-Man's Collection of Photographs 1892-1933
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
John Well-Off-Man's Collection of Photographs
1892-1933
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 924
Well-Off-Man, John, b. 1950
109 photographs
John Well-Off-Man’s collection of photographs contains images of what is now the Rocky Boy's Indian Reservation from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. While the images in the collection come from several sources, the majority are believed to have been taken by John Gable, the son of William Gable, the Lutheran Pastor on the Rocky Boy Reservation in the 1920s, 30s, and 40s.
Biographical Note
John Well-Off-Man is a member of the Chippewa-Cree Tribe. Born in Havre, Montana in 1950, Well-Off-Man was raised on the nearby Rocky Boy's Indian Reservation. In 1978, he received a degree in photography from the Ohio Visual Arts Institute after which he studied printmaking at the Institute of American Indian Arts in New Mexico where he received an Associate of Fine Arts degree in 1990. Continuing his education, Well-Off-Man earned a Bachelor of Arts in Fine Arts from the University of Montana in 2005 and a Master of Arts in Fine Arts, Integrated Arts, and Education from the University of Montana's Creative Pulse Program in 2007. Well-Off-Man has worked as a photographer, film developer, and artist.
John Well-Off-Man's Collection of Photographs contains 109 images of people and events on the Rocky Boy's Indian Reservation. The photographs were taken during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Well-Off-Man collected these images from Paul Mitchell, an elder from Rocky Boy's Indian Reservation, as part of his research into the history of the Rocky Boy Reservation. Well-Off-Man made copy negatives from Mitchell's nitrate negatives.
A portion of the images in this collection have brief descriptions written on them, though it is not clear by whom. Almost all the images are undated and many currently lack identification of the individuals in them. Most are of Cree and Ojibwe (Chippewa) people. While the images in the collection come from several sources, the majority were likely taken by John Gable, the son of William Gable who was the Lutheran Pastor on the Rocky Boy Reservation in the 1920s, 30s, and 40s. As a graduate student at the Philadelphia Seminary in the 1930s, John Gable was also responsible for a number of film productions including "Rocky Boy Mission In Action," a 1935 film about the Lutheran Mission on the Rocky Boy Reservation. While it is unclear whether the photos in this collection are associated with Gable's documentary project, the content of the images suggest that there is a connection between the two. According to Well-Off-Man other images were taken by Florence Bruckner.
Images were maintained in the order in which they were received.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
These images were held by John Well-Off-Man who acquired them from Paul Mitchell, an elder on the Rocky Boy's Indian Reservation.
John Well-Off-man donated these images to the Archives in 1988 and 1989.
The Evangelical Lutheran Church in America holds the John W. Gable motion picture film collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Well-Off-Man, John Phillip, 1950---Archives; Little Bear Cree chief, 1851-1921--Photographs; Rocky Boy (Ojibwa chief)--Photographs
Chippewa-Cree Indians of the Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana--Photographs
Rocky Boy's Reservation (Mont.)--Photographs
Montana; Native Americans
Photographs
- Man Standing Beside Teepee, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0001)
- Bob Small "Bob Tail" KES-KAH-YO, 1906; Bob Small 'Bob Tail' KES-KAH-YO in full Indian dress on Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. The boy wears leggings, moccasins, and a beaded choker. He stands in front of a tipi. (Name of photographer and date of photograph from Montana Historical Society.); Photographer: Peeso, F. E. (Frederick Edwin), 1881-1970 (Box 1, Photo number 89.0002)
- Portrait of Little Bear (Cree), undated; Photo portrait of Little Bear of the Cree. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0003)
- Portrait of Chief Kenawash., undated; Photo Portrait of Chief Kenawash. He wears a beaded belt.; Photographer: Fritz Studio (Box 1, Photo number 89.0004)
- Portrait of Little Bear with pipe, circa 1895; Photo portrait of Little Bear with pipe on Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0005)
- Studio portrait of Little Bear and an unidentified man, undated; Studio portrait of Little Bear and an unidentified white man with a large mustache. Little Bear wears leggings and a headdress. He stands with his hand on the seated man's shoulder. A dog stands between them. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0006)
- Portrait of Left Hand Boy, circa 1919; Studio portrait of Left Hand Boy on Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0007)
- Portrait of Chief Kenawash, undated; Studio portrait of Chief Kenawash on Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. He wears a headdress.; Photographer: Fritz Studio (Box 1, Photo number 89.0008)
- Studio Portrait of Jim Denny Family, undated; Studio photo of Jim Denny, "Maggie" Denny, William Denny, and Florana Denny on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0009)
- White Bear Claws with his horse, undated; White Bear Claws with his horse on the Rocky Boy Reservation. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0010)
- Old Boy O-CHA-SE-MAS, undated; A picture of 'Old Boy' O-cha-se-mas, wrapped in a blanket, on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. He stands on a blanket in front of what appears to be a tipi. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0011)
- Church chapel, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0012)
- Indian family, undated; A picture of an unidentified Indian family, likely on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. A woman and six children stand in front of a tipi. Library note: The family is identified in a Montana Historical Society photo in MMP as the Smallboy family. The boy in the front row on the right side of the photo wearing decorative leggings is Robert Smallboy (Bobtail). (Box 1, Photo number 89.0013)
- Edward Arkinson, Baptiste Samatt, and Edward Eagleman, undated; Indian man and two boys in full dress: Edward Arkinson, Baptiste Samatt, and Edward Eagleman on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. They stand in front of painted tipis. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0014)
- Indian family standing in front of building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0015)
- Indian man standing with a shovel, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0016)
- Indian standing in front of building in winter, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0017)
- Indian family standing in front of a teepee, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0018)
- Two workers making a support for a structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0019)
- Havre, Montana, undated; Scene in Havre, Montana. A group of Native Americans are in a circle in the street with people gathered around. A number of horse-drawn wagons are in the circle. Broadwater Brothers Drugs storefront is visible. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0020)
- Family in front of car, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0021)
- Rosie Two Teeth beading a bag and a belt, undated; Rosie Two Teeth beading a bag and a belt on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0022)
- Portrait of Charlie Chippewa, undated; Portrait of Charlie Chippewa, brother of Chief Rocky Boy. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0023)
- People standing in front of building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0024)
- Portrait of Grace Crazy Boy of the Rocky Boy Reservation, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0025)
- Portrait of Chief Rocky Boy, undated; Rocky Boy, Ojibwa Chief. Deer Lodge, Montana (Box 1, Photo number 89.0026)
- Big Rock, circa 1916; Picture of Big Rock, medicine man of the Chippewa, in front of teepee or lodge furnished by Charles M. Russell on a lot at the rear of Theodore Gibson's home in Great Falls, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0029)
- Native Americans, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0030)
- Portrait of George Watson (White Head)., circa 1916; Studio portrait of George Watson (White Head). He wears a beaded vest and other beaded clothing. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0031)
- Sun Dance Structure, undated; Sun dance structure on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. Several Native Americans are in and around the structure. One is on horseback. Two others sit in a wagon. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0032)
- Cross mounted on a stone structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0033)
- Indian children eating lunch, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0034)
- Pioneer town and wagons, undated; Pioneer town with wagons, likely in Montana. The town sits in a valley. The wagons and at least one automobile are on a hill above the town. An American flag flies near the wagons. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0035)
- Chief Little Bear, undated; Portrait of Chief Little Bear of the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. He sits on a blanket with a blanket covering his legs. Part of a pole-framed structure can be seen, and one of the poles casts a shadow across Chief Little Bear's face and torso. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0036)
- Mary Chief Out, undated; Mary Chief Out holding a baby, Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. She stands in front of a log building. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0037)
- Council Sun Dance Camp, undated; Council sun dance camp, Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. A group of Native Americans sit in a circle. Several men on horseback are just outside the circle. Many of the men wear Native American attire; some wear headdresses. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0038)
- Group of people listening to sermon, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0039)
- Group of Indians doing a dance, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0040)
- Mr. and Mrs. Joe Black Tongue standing in front of a log house, Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0041)
- Old Council Hall, undated; A picture of the old Council Hall built before 1920 on the Rocky Boy Reservation. Snow is visible on the ground and on parts of the wooden structure. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0042)
- Sun Dance Structure, undated; Group of men and women around the Sun Dance Structure. Probably at Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. Structure is partially covered with canvas and wooden poles are visible. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0043)
- Teepee, undated; Cooking utensils displayed in front of teepee. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0044)
- A group of Native American women and children, undated; A group of Native American women and children pose in front of a building. Library note: The building is probably the Our Saviour's Lutheran Church on the Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. Many of the women in the photograph are wrapped in blankets. The children wear coats and hats. Other buildings can be seen behind the group. The soft-top of a buggy or an old car is visible behind the women on the left side of the photograph, and two horses, presumably hitched to a buggy, are on the right side of the photograph. A hillside is visible behind the buildings. This is the same group of people that appear in image umt010861. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0045)
- A child standing in front of a car, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0046)
- Native Americans in field. Arrow on negative points to "Dad", undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0047)
- Native Americans. Male, female, and child in full dress, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0048)
- Two Indians performing a dance in full dress in front of a wooden cross, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0049)
- Native Americans and others standing in front of a building, Frank Linderman far right., 1913; Left to Right: Chief Little Bear, Kinnewash, William Bole, Franklin K. Lane (Secretary of the Interior), Jim Denny, Other Person, Pat Raspberry, Frank Bird Linderman in front of Placer Hotel, Helena, 1913. During the conference on securing land for Chief Little Bear and his tribe (description from Image 48 in Frank Bird Linderman Collection, University of Montana.); Photographer: Taylor Studio (Helena, Montana) (Box 1, Photo number 89.0050)
- Mrs. Alec Denny and grandson during a circle dance, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0051)
- The Medicine Lodge on Rocky Boy Reservation>, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0052)
- Going after the Sun Dance Tree on horseback, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0053)
- Clothing Give-Away For Women., undated; A group of unidentified women and children stand outdoors. The large building on the right behind the group is Our Saviour's Lutheran Church on the Rocky Boy's Reservation in Montana. Many of the women are wrapped in blankets. The children wear coats and hats. Several dogs wander in front of the group. Another building can be seen behind the group on the left side of the photo. A soft-top vehicle is visible behind the women on the left side of the photo. A hillside rises behind the buildings. This is the same group of people that appear in umt011117. Image is titled: Clothing give-away for women. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0054)
- People parked in cars outside a house at a clothing give-away for women on the Rocky Boy Reservation, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0055)
- Indian looking at a structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0056)
- Our Saviour's Lutheran Church original building, circa 1930s; The log building in the center of the photo is the original log chapel of Our Saviour's Lutheran Mission Church on the Rocky Boy's Reservation. A large number of parked cars is parked near the buildings. The vintage of the cars in the photograph suggest the photo was taken in the early to mid-1930s. A number of people, perhaps the congregration, stand outside the chapel. The chapel is near Boxelder Creek. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0057)
- Decoration Day, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0058)
- The first Rocky Boy School and the first Superintendant of the reservation, Mr. Parker, in the cap, circa 1927; The first Rocky Boy School and the first Superintendent of the reservation, Mr. Parker, wearing the cap. A group of adults and children pose for the photographer in front of a log building. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0059)
- Cecilia Parker and Bessie Well-Off-Man, undated; Cecilia Parker and Bessie Well-Off-Man standing in front of a house. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0060)
- Group of Indian people resting and watching, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0061)
- Decoration Day, undated; Celebration during Decoration Day. Young girls holding ribbons around a tree. Possibly on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0062)
- Indian Peace Flag of 1803, June 1933; Two Native American men and Frank Linderman hold an Indian Peace Flag of 1803 with Frank Linderman on the right. Library note: The man on the left is Jim Gopher (Loud Thunder), and the man in the middle is Frenchman. The flag is thin, and the bodies of the men holding the flag can be seen through it. Another man can be seen though the flag kneeling on the ground and holding the bottom of the flag beside Linderman. What appears to be a Sun Dance structure is being erected in the background. Same as image umt010345. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0063)
- A group of Indians sitting inside the Sun Dance structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0064)
- People using farm equipment, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0065)
- Two couples standing beside a log house, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0066)
- Group of Indian men and women standing in front of a clump of trees>, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0067)
- Sun Dance Structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0068)
- Men standing in front of an unfinished house, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0069)
- Indians in full dress in the middle of a town street, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0070)
- Indians standing on a platform for building a structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0071)
- Portrait of an Indian, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0072)
- Sun Dance Camp, undated; A picture of the Sun dance camp on the plain. Location unknown (probably Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana.) (Box 1, Photo number 89.0073)
- Unidentified building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0074)
- Sun Dance Structure, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0075)
- Celebrating at the Sun Dance Camp, undated; Indians celebrate at the sun dance camp, likely on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. Men, women, and children can be seen in the foreground. Some are on horseback; others are in wagons. Most of the people stand. Several automobiles are parked near the crowd. The sun dance structure can be seen in the middle of the photograph, and tents or tipis are in the background. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0076)
- Indians cooking at a cooking fire, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0077)
- A person with clothing all around, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0078)
- Buildings on the plain, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0079)
- Charley Black Tongue and (?) Sleek with horses in front of building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0080)
- Unidentified men standing in front of building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0081)
- Jim Gopher (Loud Thunder), Frenchman and Frank Linderman (right) holding an American flag, undated; Two Native American men and Frank Linderman hold an Indian Peace Flag of 1803 with Frank Linderman on the right. Library note: The man on the left is Jim Gopher (Loud Thunder), and the man in the middle is Frenchman. The flag is thin, and the bodies of the men holding the flag can be seen through it. Another man can be seen though the flag kneeling on the ground and holding the bottom of the flag beside Linderman. What appears to be a Sun Dance structure is being erected in the background. Same as image umt010345. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0082)
- Group on Street in Havre, Montana, 1892; A group of men and women gather on the street in Havre, Montana. Some are on horseback, most are standing. Many (all?) are Native American. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0083)
- Sun Dance Camp, undated; Indians celebrating at the Sun dance camp. The sun dance structure, an open, circular framework of logs, is seen in the mid background. Tents are visible farther back. (Probably Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana.) (Box 1, Photo number 89.0084)
- People helping to build the first jail on the Rocky Boy Reservation, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0085)
- Three buildings, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0086)
- Indians standing in front of cooking fire, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0087)
- A saw used for making lumber, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0088)
- Group of Indians standing in front of a building, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0089)
- Rocky Boy Mission and Post Office, undated; Rocky Boy Mission and Post Office. Montana. Log-sided building set at the base of a mountain. Signs on front of building read US Post Office and Rocky Boy Mission. A second building can be seen in the background on right of photograph. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0090)
- Women at Council Hall, undated; Women and children pose for a photo in front of Council Hall. Many of the women wear blankets. The hall is a log building. Probably at Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0091)
- Men at Council Hall, undated; Men and boys pose for a photo outside of Council Hall. The men wear traditional Native American garb, and most have some form of headdress. The hall is a log building. Probably at Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0092)
- Bringing in the Sun Dance Pole, undated; A group of people on horses. Image is entitled: Bringing in the sun dance pole. (Probably Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana.) (Box 1, Photo number 89.0093)
- Four babies on a blanket, undated; Four babies sitting on a blanket. A woman is visible in the far right of the image. Infants appear to be Native Americans. Background appears washed out due to sunshine. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0094)
- Lumber Yard, undated; Men and horses working in a lumber yard and mill on the Rocky Boy Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0095)
- Woman inside an Indian Reservation car, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0096)
- The Plains, undated; Teepee, tent and people on plains of Montana. Mountains in background. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0097)
- Unidentified town, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0098)
- Summer homes on the flat, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0099)
- Sun Dance Pole, undated; A picture of the Sun Dance Pole. Men seated and standing near it. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0100)
- Winter homes on the flat, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0101)
- Indians at the Sun Dance Camp, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0102)
- Tommy Oats on his horse, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0103)
- Sun Dance structure, undated; Sun Dance structure. Men seated and standing nearby. Two men on horseback. Army-style tents and hills in background. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0104)
- Structures abandoned, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0105)
- Indian children, undated; Group of Indian boys and girls of various ages stand in front of a building that may be a schoolhouse. Probably at Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0106)
- Celebrating at the Sun Dance, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0107)
- Going to the Mission by sled, undated; People on a horse-drawn sled going to the Mission on the Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. Several women sit on the sled. A man and a women stand. The people appear to be Native American. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0108)
- Man in house with buffalo skin, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0109)
- Larry Spotted Blanket and Bill Watson, undated; Larry Spotted Blanket and Bill Watson. Watson sits on a horse-drawn disk plowing a field. Location is probably Rocky Boy's Reservation, Montana. (Box 1, Photo number 89.0110)
- Father and son in full Indian dress, undated (Box 1, Photo number 89.0111)